<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some papers of the Commissioners of Scotland given in lately to the Houses of Parliament, concerning the propositions of peace.</title>
            <title>Proceedings. 1646</title>
            <author>Scotland. Convention of Estates.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92615</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1346</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E333_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200741</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895206</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895206</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152728</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92615)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152728)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2318:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some papers of the Commissioners of Scotland given in lately to the Houses of Parliament, concerning the propositions of peace.</title>
                  <title>Proceedings. 1646</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Convention of Estates.</author>
                  <author>Buchanan, David, 1595?-1652?</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. Proceedings. 1646.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Robert Bostock, dwelling at the signe of the Kings Head in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>April 11. 1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The papers are dated March 16, March 26 and April 6, 1646.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: on verso of leaf A2: "This written by Mr David Buchanan".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152728:1"/>
            <p>SOME PAPERS OF THE COMMISSIONERS OF SCOTLAND, Given in lately to the Houſes of PARLIAMENT, <hi>Concerning the PROPOSITIONS</hi> OF Peace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Robert Boſtock,</hi> dwelling at the ſigne of the Kings Head in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. <hi>April</hi> 11. 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:152728:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152728:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Judicious and good Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe drawing up of Propoſitions for Peace to be ſent unto the King, for a long time hath taken up the thoughts and pains of thoſe who ſit at the ſtern and helm of affairs. The delay of ſending the Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, of late hath buſied the phancies and tongues of moſt men, who do make it at this time the ordinary Theme of their diſcourſes, which every one frameth right or wrong as he is carried by intereſt, but chiefly and mainly as he is lead by information, reaſoning to and fro, he layeth the cauſe of the thus delaying to ſend Propoſitions to His Majeſty, upon thoſe whom he thinks and giveth out to be the let.</p>
            <p>Now, ſeeing the great miſtake of many well-minded men in this Point, who taking things at the ſecond hand, without being able to dive to the bottome and ground of affairs, ſhut at rovers and do not attain the mark; For the better information of all thoſe who love Truth; and that faithful men with conſtancy to the Principles whereunto we are all ſworn by our ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn
<pb facs="tcp:152728:3"/> Covenant, and tyed to by divers Treaties, Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Reſults, after ſo many debates, confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, and mature deliberation, be no more thus miſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtod, as they are by ſome, namely by thoſe who are ſo much concerned to know the truth; and conſequently to reject the ſiniſtrous reports, raiſed and ſpred abroad against honeſty, integrity, with constant faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the glory of God and good of his People: I having clearly underſtood from very good intelligence the cauſe in hand, do ſet it down here truely and ſimply as it is <hi>revera,</hi> without any diſguiſement by ſtating the question otherwayes then it is indeed, or by colouring it with affected words; which I here preſent unto thee, judicious Reader, heartily for thy ſatisfaction; with the Copy of three Papers given into the Houſes of Parliament by the Commiſſioners of <hi>Scotland,</hi> which the laſt day fell into my hands; I pray thee to take in good part this weak expreſſion for the publike good from him who conſtantly prayeth for the welfare of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and wiſheth thee to live in it happily and proſperouſly,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Adieu.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152728:3"/>
            <head>The ſtate of the Queſtion concerning the Propoſitions of Peace.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Commiſſioners of <hi>Scotland</hi> have for nine Moneths, ever ſince the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth of <hi>Iune</hi> laſt, preſſed the ſending of the former Propoſitions agreed upon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Kingdomes, preſented to the King at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and whereof the moſt materiall were afterward debated upon at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Houſes of Parliament upon the ſixth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, in anſwer to the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Commiſſioners declare, That Propoſitions ſhall be ſent ſpeedily, but that they intend to make ſome alterations.</p>
            <p>After nine Moneths the Houſes deliver to the <hi>Scots</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners upon the laſt of <hi>February</hi> ſome new Propoſitions.</p>
            <p>The Commiſſioners of <hi>Scotland</hi> upon the 16. of <hi>Marchs</hi> deliver in their Anſwer to theſe Propoſitions, wherein they obſerve, that all the omiſſions, additions, or alteration made in the former Propoſitions, are in thoſe things which concerne the joynt intereſt and union of the Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>Upon the 26. of <hi>March</hi> the Houſes appoint a Committee
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152728:4"/> to debate with the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Commiſſioners concerning the differences, which are chiefly theſe:</p>
            <p n="1">1 Concerning Religion; The Houſes make a generall Propoſition, deſiring the King to aſſent to what they have, or ſhall agree upon concerning Reformation of Religion, and concerning Uniformity in Religion, as the two King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms ſhall agree.</p>
            <p>The Commiſſioners deſire to know the particulars, that after ſo long conſultation of the Divines of both Kingdoms, they may with knowledge and aſſurance conſent to that Propoſition; it was anſwered, the Houſes had not reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved what particulars to ſend: And the Commiſſioners of <hi>Scotland</hi> deny to conſent till they be acquainted with the Particulars, and take them into conſideration.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Concerning the <hi>Militia,</hi> The Commiſſioners deſire the former Propoſition agreed upon between the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and debated at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge</hi> to be ſent, eſpecially becauſe it doth neerly unite the Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>The Houſes in their new Propoſitions will have the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia</hi> of the Kingdomes ſetled ſeverally, each Kingdome by it ſelfe apart.</p>
            <p>The Commiſſioners deſire ſuch a conjunction at leaſt, as both may upon occaſion joyne together for ſuppreſſing inſurrections, and oppoſing forraigne invaſions.</p>
            <p>The Houſes will have the <hi>Militia</hi> ſetled in themſelves from time to time without any limitation, and not only the King, but his Poſterity and the Crowne excluded in time comming.</p>
            <p>The Commiſſioners conceive it neceſſary, that for the ſecurity of the Kingdomes the <hi>Militia</hi> ſhould be ſo ſetled as the King may have no power to make theſe Kingdomes twice miſerable, but that this being a caſe extraordinary, it
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152728:4"/> ſhould onely be for a time; and as upon the one part, they thinke it moſt dangerous, that the <hi>Militia</hi> ſhould after expiration of that time be ſetled in the King alone, ſo they hold it very unſafe, That the fundamentall Lawes of the Kingdom ſhould be altered, and the Crown for ever exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from all intereſt &amp; right whatſoever; but after expiration of ſuch a time as ſhall be agreed upon, the ordering of the <hi>Militia</hi> may be by King and Parliament, according to the many Declarations of both Kingdomes,<note place="margin">See Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of Remonſt. pag. 207, 208. 728, 729, 730. &amp;c.</note> and particularly of the Houſes of Parliament, who affirme it to be by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution and fundamentall Lawes of the Kingdome in King and Parliament together, and onely in caſes extraordinary, when the King failes in his Duty, the Parliament alone to provide for the ſecurity of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Concerning <hi>Ireland;</hi> The Houſes alleadge, that the tranſ-actions between the Kingdomes made at <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> 28. <hi>November</hi> 1643. are no Treaty.</p>
            <p>The Commiſſioners make it appeare that it is a Treaty, for that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Commiſſioners had power to Treat, agree, and conclude; Articles are drawn up and agreed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, which the Houſes ratifie and confirme in their Votes of the ninth of <hi>March,</hi> and eleaventh of <hi>Aprill,</hi> 1643. In the ſame Votcs calling it a Treaty: And <hi>Scotland</hi> performes their part of the Treaty, makes their Army ſtay and advance to them a hundreth thouſand pounds ſterling, at the deſire of <hi>England,</hi> who then becauſe of their low condition were not able to ſend them any releife; and now the Houſes make queſtion to perform their part of the Treaty to <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, The difference is concerning foure Propoſitions formerly agreed upon between the Kingdomes, and omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Houſes in their new Propoſitions. They are:</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:152728:5"/>
            <p n="1">1. The Propoſition that Peace and Warre ſhall not be made without conſent of both Kingdomes. 2. For educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Kings Children by conſent of both Kingdomes 3. For disbanding the Armies by conſent of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes. 4. For an Act of oblivion by conſent of both.</p>
            <p>The Commiſſioners deſire, that either the Propoſitions concerning Religion, the <hi>Militia,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> be ſent alone as was done at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge,</hi> or if more be ſent, That theſe Propoſitions which concerne the joynt intereſt of both Kingdomes may alſo be ſent when others of leſſe moment are ſent.</p>
            <p>When the Committee of both Houſes, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners had debated upon all theſe differences, the Commiſſioners expected that both ſhould have joyned their endeavours to finde out expedients for removing theſe differences, and ſo come to a ſpeedy agreement. But the Committee of both Houſes, Declared they had no power to conſent to the alteration of the leaſt circumſtance, though they were convinced in reaſon; whereupon the Commiſſioners gave in a Paper, deſiring the Houſes to enlarge the power of the Committee.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152728:5"/>
            <head>Some Papers of the Commiſſioners of <hi>Scotland,</hi> given in lately to the Houſes of PARLIAMENT: Concerning the Propoſitions of Peace.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ur earneſt deſires to have Religion ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in this Kingdome according to the Covenant, and to have both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes delivered from their preſent troubles and preſſures, and eſtabliſhed in a firme and happy peace, that we our ſelves and our Army might returne to our owne Native Country with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and contentment; moved us theſe nine Moneths paſt often and earneſtly to preſſe, That the Propoſitions for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly agreed upon by the two Kingdomes might be ſent to his Majeſty, and the Anſwer of the Honourable Houſes ſeaven moneths ſithence; ſhewing their reſolution to ſend Propoſitions to his Majeſty for ſuch a Peace, hath moved us extreamly to long for them. Upon the 28. of <hi>February</hi> we received ſome of the Propoſitions, which your Lordſhips deſire to be ſent, and in anſwer to our Paper of the ſecond
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152728:6"/> of this inſtant <hi>March,</hi> expreſſing our deſire to know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe were all the Propoſitions deſired to be ſent, or if we were to expect any other. It was returned upon the fourth of <hi>March,</hi> that theſe were all, except ſuch as concern Delinquents, and the City, which were ſpeedily to be delivered unto us.</p>
            <p>In the Propoſitions which we have received we cannot but obſerve, That the moſt materiall additions, omiſſions, and alterations as they are expreſſed in the Paper wherein the difference conſiſts, betwixt theſe and the Propoſitions formerly agreed upon, doe trench upon the joynt intereſt of both Kingdomes, and tend to the leuſing of the Bonds, and weakning of the ſinews of our happy Union: which were not only notable Pledges and Evidences of reciprocall kindneſſe for the time, to the diſcouragement of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Enemy, but were alſo powerfull meanes for conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and perpetuating our common Peace, and Brotherly Amity for all Generations to come, to the diſpairing of all our Enemies, ever to prevaile by their plots or attempts againſt theſe ſo neerly and firmly united Kingdomes. This could not but be a matter of reſentment and unſpeakeable griefe unto us, and to the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> had we not grounds of aſſurance of the intention of both Houſes to the contrary; both from the inviolable League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, wherein we have all ſworne, to <hi>endeavour that theſc Kingdomes may remaine conjoyned in a firme Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion to all poſterity,</hi> and from their Letter of the 13. of <hi>November,</hi> 1645. to the Parliament of <hi>Scotland,</hi> expreſſing their deſire of a nearer union, and conjunction between the Kingdomes: We come therefore to the particular conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Propoſitions. We doe firſt of all deſire, That the Preface, Title, and concluſion of the Propoſitions may be the ſame as formerly, or to that ſence.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:152728:6"/>
            <p>In the firſt Article we deſire theſe words <hi>[the Parliament of that Kingdome]</hi> to be added after theſe words <hi>[conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Eſtates in Scotland]</hi> and we doe agree to the firſt, ſecond, third, and fourth Propoſitions.</p>
            <p>To the fifth and ſixth Propoſitions, We deſire to ſee what the Houſes have already agreed upon concerning Religion, and then we ſhall give in our Anſwer about theſe Propoſitions.</p>
            <p>To the 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, and 12. Propoſitions wee doe agree, the clauſe ſet downe in the 11. Article of the former Propoſitions, and omitted in theſe, concerning the ratifying the Acts of the Convention of Eſtates and Parliament of <hi>Scotland,</hi> being added to the 12. Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</p>
            <p>The Treaty at <hi>Edenburgh</hi> the 28. of <hi>Nov.</hi> 1643. which was comprehended in the former Propoſition agreed upon between the Kingdomes, is excluded by theſe words in this new 13. Propoſition <hi>[And whereunto they are obliged by the afareſaid Treaties]</hi> for the Kingdomes were not obliged by any of the former Treaties to make a ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Treaty, and therefore we deſire the ſaid Treaty of the 28. of <hi>Nov.</hi> 1643. together with the Ordinances of the 9. of <hi>March,</hi> and the 11. of <hi>Aprill,</hi> ratifying the ſame, may be expreſſed in the Propoſition, for which we offer the Reaſons following:</p>
            <p>The Commiſſioners of the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived particular inſtructions from the two Houſes to treat with the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> concerning the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Army in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and ordering thereof in ſuch manner as might beſt conduce to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of that Warre according to the ends expreſſed in the Covenant. And by their inſtructions communicated to the Convention of Eſtates of <hi>Scotland,</hi> according to the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152728:7"/> direction of the Houſes, they are expreſly authorized to ſettle upon ſome courſe with the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to manage the War by the joynt advice of the Committees of both Kingdomes, and to prevent the evills and miſchiefs that elſe might fall out for want of the ſame.</p>
            <p>According to theſe inſtructions ſeven Articles are mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally agreed upon at <hi>Edenburgh</hi> the 28. of <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1643. by a Committee of both Kingdomes, after adviſing with the Agents and Officers ſent from the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Army, and ſerious debates, and mature deliberation upon the whole matter between the Committees of both Kingdomes, as is acknowledged in the preface of the Treaty.</p>
            <p>In the fourth Article of that Treaty two things are agreed on: 1. That he who doth or ſhall command in chief over the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Army, by joynt conſent of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, ſhall alſo command the reſt of the Britiſh Forces in <hi>Ireland.</hi> 2. For the managing of that Warre, and proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting the ends expreſſed in the Covenant, that the ſame be done by joynt advice with the Committees of both Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>Theſe Articles being agreed upon were tranſmitted to the Houſes of Parliament, and ſix of them ratified and approved in the Votes of both Houſes of the ninth of <hi>March,</hi> and eleaventh of <hi>Aprill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Votes of the ninth of <hi>March,</hi> the fourth Article concerning the Command in chiefe, and the managing of the Warre, with the joynt advice of both Kingdomes, is <hi>verbatim</hi> ratified by the Houſes, and was preſented at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge</hi> to be confirmed by the King.</p>
            <p>The Commiſſioners of <hi>Scotland</hi> having received inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions from the Eſtates of Parliament for the perfecting of this Treaty, and the two Houſes having referred the ſame to the conſideration of the Committee of both Kingdoms,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152728:7"/> After a free debate, and full deliberation the third and fourth Articles of the Treaty at Edenburgh were agreed upon and perfected by them, and reported to both Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, who ratified and approved the ſame in their votes of the 11<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>April.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the command in chiefe, theſe words were agreed upon, That the Earle of <hi>Leven</hi> Lord Generall of the Scottiſh forces in <hi>Ireland</hi> being now by the votes of both houſes agreed to be commander in chiefe over all the forces, as well Brittiſh as Scotts, according to the fourth Article of the reſult of the Committee of both kingdomes paſſed both houſes, be deſired with all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient ſpeed by the advice of the ſaid Committees, to nominate and appoint a Commander in chiefe under his Excellency over the ſaid forces to reſide with them upon the place.</p>
            <p>Concerning the managing of the warre, it is agreed upon in theſe words, That Committees be nominated and appointed by the joynt advice of both Kingdomes of ſuch numbers and qualities as ſhal be by them agreed on, to be ſent with all convenient ſpeed to reſide with the ſaid forces, &amp; enabled with full and ample inſtructions by the joynt advice of both Kingdoms, for regulating of the ſaid forces, and the better carrying on of that war. And both theſe Articles were delivered in at the Treaty at Uxbridge, and deſired to be confirmed.</p>
            <p>That according to theſe Articles, Committees are now in Ireland from both Kingdoms for mannaging of the war.</p>
            <p>That theſe Articles of the 28 of <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1643. are likewiſe ratified in the Parliament of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred as a Treaty.</p>
            <p>That the houſes of Parliament in their votes of the 9 of <hi>March</hi> do in approbation of the ſixth Article acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it to be a Treaty.</p>
            <p>That the votes of the 9 of <hi>March</hi> by direction of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152728:8"/> houſes were delivered unto us, as their conſent to the Articles of the ſaid Treaty of the 28 of <hi>November,</hi> and the houſes in their Letter of the 25 of <hi>May</hi> did acquaint the Parliament of <hi>Scotland</hi> that they had ratified and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed the ſeverall Treaties made and agreed between their Commiſſioners, and the Convention of Eſtates of <hi>Scotland:</hi> And that it was their deſire the ſame might be done by the Parliament of <hi>Scotland,</hi> which they did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly.</p>
            <p>That theſe Articles were agreed upon between the Kingdomes when the Parliaments Army in <hi>Munſter</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted from them, and when the Scottiſh Army in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> had ſent agents to the Convention of Eſtates of <hi>Scotland</hi> to declare, that by reaſon of their extreame wants and ſufferings occaſioned by the want of their pay and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary maintenance, due by the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> they were reſolved to leave that Kingdome, whereby it would have been wholly loſt to the Parliament of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> if the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> had not interpoſed, and by taxing great ſums of money upon the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and levying proviſions, had raiſed conſiderable ſupplies, and ſent them over for the preſent ſubſiſtence of the Scottiſh Army, untill the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> ſhould be able to ſend them further ſupplies; which both Houſes doe acknowledge in their ſaid Letter of the 25 of <hi>May</hi> to the Parliament of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and doe return their hearty thanks to the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> for their care of that Army, and the great charge they have been at for their reliefe with proviſions and money for their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary ſubſiſtence.</p>
            <p>Thoſe Articles being treated upon by Committees of both Kingdomes, both in <hi>Scotland</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> being ratified by the Parliaments of both Kingdomes, and by both acknowledged to be a Treaty; preſented with the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152728:8"/> Propoſitions of peace, and debated at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge,</hi> and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving as much if not more of the formalities of a Treaty then the firſt Treaty concerning the ſending of the Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Army into <hi>Ireland:</hi> we deſire this Treaty may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted with the other Treaties in this Propoſition, it being moſt reaſonable the Treaty made and conditions agreed on for the continuance of that ſtarved Army in <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſhould be of as great force and as well obſerved, as the Treaty made for ſending them over into <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to the former part of the 14 Propoſition, we deſire it may ſtand as formerly, for the reaſons above expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: And as to the later part now added, we deſire that all the Articles concerning the ſetling of Religion in this Kingdome may be extended to <hi>Ireland,</hi> according to the Covenant.</p>
            <p>The 15 Propoſition concerning Delinquents we have not received.</p>
            <p>To the 16 and 17 Propoſitions we do agree.</p>
            <p>In the 18 Propoſition, we find ſo materiall differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces from that which was formerly agreed upon concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Militia, as may be matter of long debate what may be moſt conducible to the ſecurity of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and ſo retard the ſending of the Propoſitions and looſe the preſent opportunity of obtaining his Majeſties conſent before he be engaged in ſome other deſign which may be a ruine to himſelfe, and a matter of new trouble to theſe Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>We deſire it may be conſidered, that the former Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, according to the intereſt of both Kingdomes, did ſettle a power in Commiſſioners of both Kingdoms for reſiſting all foraigne invaſions, and for ſuppreſſing of all forces raiſed within either of the ſaid Kingdoms, to the diſturbance of their peace; By which there was no place left either to arbitrary power, or to any miſtake or jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152728:9"/> that could be raiſed or fomented between the Kingdoms; or to any project of Incendiaries, to divide the King from any of his Kingdomes, or one Kingdome from another. And we ſee no reaſon why that which at the framing of theſe Propoſitions, was eſteemed as a great ſervice and a firme foundation of unity and mutuall confidence betwixt the Kingdomes, ſhould now be alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, the reaſons for preventing thereof being as ſtrong as ever. And this new Propoſition containes nothing that may prevent thoſe ſo great and obvious inconveniences, but ſeems rather to argue a diffidence and jealouſie to the weakning of that mutuall confidence which was laid by the former Propoſitions.</p>
            <p>Further, this new Propoſition doth not provide how the Militia ſhall be ordered and diſpoſed in the Intervals of Parliament, although in another caſe by the 21 Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition concerning the nomination of the Deputy or chief Governour of <hi>Ireland</hi> the Chancellor or Lord Keeper, Lord Treaſurer, and other Officers and miniſters of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> it is provided that in the Intervals of Parliament they ſhall be nominated by a Committee of Parliament. And if it be intended that in like manner the Militia be ordered in the intervals of Parliament by a Committee of Parliament, there is no objection can be made againſt the former Propoſition, for ſetling the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia in Commiſſioners, which will not be as full againſt ſetling thereof in a Committee, for by the former Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions the Commiſſioners were alterable from time to time by the Houſes, and to receive and obſerve their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections and inſtructions.</p>
            <p>Wee conceive alſo, as the honourable Houſes upon conſideration of the manifold troubles and diſtractions in theſe times, have wiſely and neceſſarily reſolved for the ſafety and ſecurity of theſe Kingdoms, ſo to ſettle the Militia, as the King although he were willing be not able
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152728:9"/> by involving them again into a bloudy warre, to make them twice miſerable wherein we are ready moſt hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to concurre: So doe we thinke, it is not their intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to diveſt the King his poſterity and Crowne for all time coming, of all power, right, and intereſt in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Militia, ſo as although they be never ſo willing to follow the adviſe of their Parliaments, yet they ſhall for ever be incapable, and in no time comming be admitted to joyne with the Parliaments, for reſſiſting their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and protecting their Subjects; the apprehenſion whereof, may prolong the Kings anſwer and hinder his conſent, and (as may eaſily be collected from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridg</hi>) may be interpreted to be a fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall alteration of the Government, contrary to the reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions and declarations of both Kingdomes, and not ſo agreeable to the Covenant; may be made uſe of by our adverſaries, for ſuch an occaſion of quarrelling, as they never had before, may be made a meane to bring the common cauſe and our cariage into contempt, &amp; uſed by our enemies as a motive for provoking foreigne Princes and States to engage in a war againſt us; both parts were provided for in the former Propoſition upon the one part the exerciſe and execution of the Militia was not to be in the power of the King, yet upon the other part were the Commiſſioners in whoſe hands it was to be truſted, to have their Commiſſion from King and Parliament, and it was condeſcended upon at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge,</hi> that the time ſhould be limited to ſeven yeares, and after expiration of that terme to be ſetled and exerciſed in ſuch manner as his Majeſty and the Parliaments of both Kingdomes reſpective ſhould thinke fit, but by this new Propoſition the whole power is to be ſetled in the two houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and the Crown altogether excluded from all intereſt in the Militia for ever, which therefore requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a new conſideration.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:152728:10"/>
            <p>There is another thing which we profeſſe doth very much affect us, that wheras in the large Treaty of Peace, a Commiſſion for preſervation of the peace then ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led between the kingdomes was judged moſt neceſſary, and was mutually agreed upon, and accordingly in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance thereof, Commiſſioners were appointed by the Parliament of Scotland, to whom the Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon ſeveral occaſions made their addreſſes to good purpoſe, and whereas in the former Propoſitions, ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Articles were ſet downe with mutuall conſent for conſerving the peace, firmely and inviolably for all time to come, yet in this new Propoſition although the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger be no leſſe, and the neceſſity no leſſe urgent, there is not ſo much as mention made of any meane to be uſed or courſe to be taken for conſerving the peace between the Kingdomes, and betwixt the King and either of them, but all paſſed in ſilence; All which neceſſary conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions we offer to the wiſdome of the honourable Houſes, that they may continue in their reſolution to ſend the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Propoſitions as they were propoſed at <hi>Vxbridge,</hi> which will be free of debate, are more likely to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained of the Kings Majeſty, and will ſerve more for the peace and good correſpondence of the Kindomes, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially that the conſervation of peace for the future may be provided for.</p>
            <p>To the 19. and 20. Propoſitions we doe agree.</p>
            <p>To the 21. Propoſition we do agree with this addition.</p>
            <p>The like for the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> concerning the nomination of the Lords of the Privie Councell, Lords of Seſſion, and Exchequer Officers of State and Juſtice Generall, in ſuch manner as the Eſtates in Parliament ſhall thinke fit.</p>
            <p>The Propoſition concerning the education, marriage, and chooſing of the Tutors and Governours of the Kings children by conſent of both Kingdomes, is omitted in theſe new Propoſitions.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:152728:10"/>
            <p>The Propoſition concerning the making of peace or war with foreigne Princes and States, with advice and conſent of both Kingdomes, is alſo omitted in theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions.</p>
            <p>The Propoſition concerning the disbanding the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies by conſent of both Kingdomes is likewiſe omitted.</p>
            <p>The Propoſition for paſſing an act of oblivion in the Parliaments of both Kingdomes is omitted.</p>
            <p>Wee deſire that the Propoſition concerning the City of <hi>London,</hi> as alſo the Propoſitions concerning Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents, may be ſpeedily delivered unto us that they may be diſpatched with the reſt.</p>
            <p>Upon the whole matter, If the houſes of Parliament ſhall thinke fit for the preſent, to ſend only the three Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, concerning Religion, the Militia, and <hi>Ireland,</hi> as they were propoſed at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge</hi> we do agree. But if they think fit that more Propoſitions be ſent at this time, we do deſire that all the Propoſitions which concerne the joynt intereſt of both Kingdomes, and are omitted in the new Propoſitions, may be ſent likewiſe, although we are of the judgement that every particular, and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Propoſitions, is not of ſo great importance to theſe Kingdomes as peace and warre ſhould depend thereupon.</p>
            <p>Having thus freely in ſuch brotherly manner as the matter of peace doth require expreſſed our ſenſe of the Propoſitions delivered unto us; if there be any miſtake on our part, or if there be any point wherein the honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Houſes are not ſatisfied, we are moſt willing and ready to give and receive all brotherly ſatisfaction, by conference or otherwiſe in ſuch manner as ſhall be judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed moſt behovefull and expeditious, and to give teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of our true and earneſt deſires, and readineſſe to concurre with the honourable Houſes in all ſuch things
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152728:11"/> as upon a friendly debate, ſhall be found conduceable for procuring, ſetling and propagating ſuch a peace, as we all deſire for our common happineſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>March,</hi> 16. 1646.</p>
            <p>It is not unknown to the Honourable Houſes of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, how long a time we have waited here in patience and ſilence for the ſetling of Church-government accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Covenant, and we our ſelves know (for which we have many witneſſes, at home in the Church of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>) how zealous we have been of the honour of the Parliament in this matter; what hath been our care and induſtry to perſwade and aſſure, that although hope de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred might make the hearts of many to faint, yet when the deſire ſhould come, it would be a tree of life; And that we were not to judge of the modell of Church-go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and of uniformity with the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> by ſome praevious and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Ordinances of Parliament which were but parts of the building, but were to expect the laſt Ordinance, which would ſupply the defects of the former, and by rearing up the whole houſe in proportion and beauty, would in the end give to every judicious eye and zealous heart a full ſatisfaction. We doe alſo with thankfulneſſe acknowledge and remember the zeale of the honourable Houſes, in removing the Book of Common-prayer, in aboliſhing Epiſcopall government, and in other parts of of Reformation, and that in the time of their greateſt troubles and dangers, which maketh their work the more acceptable to God and all good men; Yet are we at this time neceſſitated by our Covenant, our common intereſt, and publique truſt, to make remonſtrance of two things moſt materiall and of greateſt conſequence: One is, that through the long delay of the ſetling of the true Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152728:11"/> of the Church, Hereſies and Sects are ſo multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, and Schiſm hath ſo much prevailed, that if there be not in time a powerful remedy provided, this Church after ſo many miſeries of a bloody and long laſting War, will be in worſe caſe then the former was, from which it was taken for a great happineſſe to be delivered; And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> after their many ſufferings in this King<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dom and at home, in greater danger then it was in from the Prelates here, whoſe uſurpation was the beginning of all our calamities and vexation.</p>
            <p>The Honourable Houſes may be pleaſed to call to minde, that in the large Treaty of the date <hi>March</hi> 10. 1641; the Commiſſioners of <hi>Scotland,</hi> from the ſenſe of the troubles of that Church, ariſing from the Prelates of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> did by many Arguments preſſe Unity in Religion, and Uniformity of Church-Government, in the three Kingdoms, Unto which from the King &amp; Parliament joynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, a comfortable and hopeful anſwer was returned for ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining their deſire. Thereafter in the yeer 1642, the General Aſſembly of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſeconded and aſſiſted by the Lords of Secret Councel, Did upon the ſame grounds renew the ſame deſire, And received from the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> not onely a Profeſſion of their great contentment in the motion propoſed, with many thanks, But alſo a large approbation of the motives upon which it was urged, which were; <q rend="inline">The more ſtrict Union of both Kingdoms; More ſafe, eaſie, and comfortable Government of his Majeſty, And both to himſelf and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple more free communion in all holy exerciſe and duties of Worſhip; More conſtant ſecurity of Religion againſt the bloody practices of Papiſts and deceitful Errors of other Sectaries; More profitable uſe of the Miniſtry, in drawing them from unpleaſant and unprofitable Controverſies,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152728:12"/> to the preſſing of Mortification, and to Treatiſes of true Piety and Practical Divinity; The making of way to the relief and deliverance of the poor afflicted Churches abroad, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> All which are expreſſed in their Declaration and Reſolution, in anſwer to the Declaration of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Aſſembly, Together with a ſad Complaint, that the miſerable Eſtate of this Church and Kingdom, was not able to endure any longer delay, And a deſire that ſome godly and learned Divines might be ſent from the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> whereby the ſo-much-deſired Unity and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity might be obtained. In the end, the mutual and joynt deſires of both Kingdoms were concluded, and crowned with a Solemn League and Covenant, now tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated in other Tongues, and known thorowout all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom; which was taken, as for other good ends, ſo for endeavouring the neereſt Conjunction and Uniformity in Religion and Church-Government, and the extirpation of Hereſie and Schiſm. All which conſidered, we may be bold to ſay without Preface or Apologie (which about the like purpoſe the Houſes of Parliament in that their Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration judged unneceſſary) that it would be the ſin and ſhame of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> And the ſorrow of all the Reformed Churches, particularly of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> if after ſo many preparations, and ſo Solemn League and Covenant is entred into, for endeavouring the neereſt Conjunction and Uniformity in Religion and Church-Goverhment, and the extirpation of Hereſie and Schiſm; Not onely all ſorts of Blaſphemies, Hereſies and Sects which are now multiplied, and Liberty of conſcience which is pleaded for, ſhould have place; But Unity and Uniformity in Religion, which is ſo much preached and written againſt, ſhould be ſleighted, and the Covenant it ſelf wreſted and perverted to ſpeak that which it never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152728:12"/> and which did not enter into any mans minde in the beginning, Such a violence as the holy Scripture it ſelf hath ſuffered from perverſe and heretical ſpirits; And this Church after ſo long a time further from Uniformity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves and with other Reformed Churches, then they were at firſt when it was judged ſo neceſſary. Againſt theſe ſo dangerous and deſtructive evils, we ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſire the Honourable Houſes to provide effectual remedy, And we pray God ſo to bleſſe their endeavours, that the ruine of Religion in both Kingdoms, with the horrid conſequences thereof, which is the work of Satan and his inſtruments, contrary to the Work of God and his Servants, may while there is yet hope, be wiſely and ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily prevented.</p>
            <p>The other material Point which we deſire to offer, is concerning the late Ordinance of Parliament, 14 <hi>March</hi> 1645, with the Directions, <hi>Aug.</hi> 19. 1645; which in diſcharge of their duty to God, in purſuance of the Covenant, and in thankfulneſſe to God for his mercies, They have after long conſultation reſolved upon; And wherein there be divers evidences of the Piety and Wiſedom of the Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Houſes, For which not onely the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and all the Reformed Churches, have cauſe to bleſſe the Lord; Yet it being acknowledged, that there may be need of Supplements and Additions, and haply alſo of alterations in ſome things, And it being ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed that the advice of the Aſſembly of Divines, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we have been aſſiſtant, is had thereunto, And we being entruſted by the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in matters that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern them ſo neerly upon their common Intereſt: We have taken the freedom to preſent our thoughts concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome particulars contained in the Ordinance.</p>
            <p>Firſt, concerning the Subordination of the Aſſemblies
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152728:13"/> of the Church to the Parliament: We make no queſtion but the Parliament is ſuperiour to all the Aſſemblies of the Church in Place, Dignity, Honour, and earthly power; That Civil powers are the Vicegerents of God on earth, And that Miniſters are onely Servants and Ambaſſadours; And that the Magiſtrate is <hi>Cuſtos utriuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tabulae,</hi> and may by his authority compel the Miniſters and Aſſemblies of the Church, to perform the duties which Chriſt requires of them: Like as the Miniſters are bound to render a reaſon and account of their proceedings to the Civil Powers with all humility and reverence. We do onely deſire, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diminution of, or derogation unto the right and juſt power of the Parliament or Civil Magiſtrate, the expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Subordination may be altered; Becauſe it may ſuppoſe (contrary to the meaning of the Parliament) that the relation of one Church-aſſembly to another, and of the Aſſemblies to the Parliament, and of appeals of one to another, are of the ſame kinde and in the ſame line, as if the Civil power were not onely about matters of the Church and Religion, But were formally Eccleſiaſtical, and to be exerciſed Eccleſiaſtically; Becauſe ſome may inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret it to be ſuch an Headſhip and Supremacy in the Church, as ſometimes was in the Pope, and hath been retained in ſubſtance in this Kingdom, As the fountain of the high-Commiſſion, and foundation of other corruptions, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the judgement of all ſuch as have ſought after fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Reformation; And becauſe it is againſt the Doctrine and Profeſſion of the Reformed Churches, which next unto the Word of God which is the Rule, are propoſed in the Covenant as the example of Reformation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, We deſire the Provincial Commiſſioners for judging of Scandals, may be taken to further conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, there being no warrant nor pretence for ſuch a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152728:13"/> in Church-Government from Jeſus Chriſt, Who hath appointed his own Spiritual Officers, to whom he hath committed the keys of the Kingdom of heaven, And to whom the Reformed Churches conceive the judging of offences, and the qualification of Communicants, doth as properly and incommunicably belong, as the publike Preaching of the Word and Adminiſtration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Nor can it be ſuppoſed, that ſome few Civil men, having no calling from God, can be more able to judge of matters of this nature, then the Aſſemblies of the Church ſeparated for the work of the Goſpel, of which this is no ſmall part. The ſame Churches, and particularly the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> which all this time have been in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of great purity and perfection of Reformation in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> may have their own jealouſies and fears, that in the nature of the thing, this may be the laying of a new foundation of an High Commiſſion or E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy, upon which the ſuperſtructure afterward, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though contrary to the preſent publike intentions, may be eaſie, And for a new partition-wall to divide betwixt them and the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and to make a preſent Schiſm and Separation for renting the bowels of this Church.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Concerning the meeting of the National Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, we acknowledge that the Supreme Magiſtrate, who is Guardian of both Tables and a Nurce-Father of the Church, may call a National Aſſembly, when in his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom he ſhall judge it neceſſary; and the Church is with all reſpect and humility to obey his call, for the good of Religion, or the Peace of the Kingdoms, when by Religion diſturbed; But it is withall to be acknowledged that this power of the Magiſtrate is accumulative or poſitive, but is not a privative or deſtructive power: We therefore
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152728:14"/> move, That the liberty which the Church hath from Chriſt be not reſtrained in caſes of ſuch extraordinary ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, as Religion in all places hath been and may be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject unto, the ſafety of the Church being here the Supreme Law, and the honourable Houſes of Parliament, having their liberties inlarged, will be willing to inlarge the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Chriſt and his Servants. And we deſire, that as they have in their wiſdom appointed certain times for the meeting of the inferior Aſſemblies of the Church, they may alſo be pleaſed to appoint fixed times for the meeting of the National Aſſembly; otherwiſe what ſhall become of the mal-adminiſtration of Provincial Synods, and of appeals from them to the National Aſſembly? May not Provincial Synods within a ſhort time run into contrary opinions and practices, and preſume upon a Provincial In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependency to hold them without controle? The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Churches in all ages have uſed this as an ordinary and neceſſary mean for the Uniform ſetling and preſerving of Religion and Piety, for cenſuring and purging out of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies and errours, and removing of ſcandals, ſchiſm, ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, prophaneneſſe, and ſuch evils as by Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and prediction muſt be, and would bring certain deſtruction and deſolation upon Churches, if by this powerful remedy they were not cured or prevented.</p>
            <p>There be divers other particulars in the Directions and Ordinance of Parliament, as the giving of the Sacrament to ſome perſons againſt the conſcience of the Miniſtry and Elderſhip, concerning publick Repentance, and ſuch like, which by conference or otherwiſe as ſhall ſeem good to the wiſdom of the honourable Houſes, we would willingly and humbly offer to be examined, and with ſmall alteration may give great ſatisfaction, being confident, that our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty in what we have expreſſed, will be taken in good
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152728:14"/> part; Sith it is done by us in purſuance of the ends of the Covenant, wherein as the Parliament &amp; Church of <hi>England</hi> are bound to endeavour the preſervation of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Diſcipline of the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> So are we bound to endeavour the Reformation of the Diſcipline and Government in the Church of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Word of God, and the example of the beſt Reformed Churches; And ſith we have not for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and we hope ſhall never have for the future, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever our adverſity or proſperity may be, any other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions or deſires, then we had and propoſed in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, when we ſo ſolemnly entred in Covenant.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>March</hi> 26. 1646.</p>
            <p>The honourable Houſes having after nine months deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration framed and upon the laſt of <hi>February</hi> delivered unto us ſome of the Propoſitions of Peace; Upon the 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>March</hi> we returned our Anſwer, in the cloſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we expreſſed our earneſt deſires and readineſſe to give and receive all brotherly ſatisfaction concerning any diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, and to concurre with the Houſes in all ſuch things as upon a friendly debate ſhould be found conduceable for procuring and ſetling a happy Peace. Upon conſideration whereof, the Houſes appointed a Committee to meet with us upon the 27<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>March:</hi> but when we expected that upon debate their Lordſhips ſhould have concurred with us in finding out expedients for removing of all dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences and reporting of the reſult to both Houſes that we might come to a ſpeedy agreement, they declared un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us that they had onely power to argue with us, and were ſo ſtrictly bound up by the Votes of the Houſes pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually to adhere to every Propoſition, that they had no
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152728:15"/> power to conſider of the alteration of the leaſt circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, though onely as preparatory and in order to the further conſideration of the Houſes. When we have ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly thought upon this way of proceeding, the Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions being the demands of both Kingdoms to be ſent in the name of both as the beſt means for ſetling a well-grounded Peace, and in regard of the joynt intereſt which both Nations have in the matter and end of the Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and according to the Treaty made between the Kingdoms, both ought to have their judgement and advice in agreeing unto, and framing of the Propoſitions; we cannot but inſiſt upon our former deſire, That the honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Houſes may be pleaſed to authorize their Committee to confer with us about the beſt way and means for remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of our differences, to propoſe expedients, and hear what ſhall be offered by us, and report the reſults to the Houſes, that ſo we may come to a ſpeedy agreement, which (if we ſhall meet with the like inclinations, as we ſhall bring with us, being reſolved as in other things ſo eſpecially in the matter of the <hi>Militia</hi> for the full ſecurity of this Kingdom as of our own, to give all poſſible ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſo far as may conſiſt with our Covenant and publick Declarations) we hope may be by Gods aſſiſtance in a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhort time effectuated. Whereas otherwiſe if we ſhall ſpend time in drawing up all our differences with the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons thereof, to preſent in writing to the Houſes, receive their anſwers, and give in replyes in like manner, it muſt needs prove the loſſe of a great deal of pretious time, may in this conjuncture of affairs be of very dangerous conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to both Kingdoms, and will retard the ſending of the Propoſitions, the diſpatch whereof for many reaſons, would not be longer delayed, eſpecially ſince we have ſo often declared to the King, that they are ſpeedily to be
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152728:15"/> ſent, and the granting of them will be an effectual means for giving ſatisfaction to both Kingdoms. This we have judged neceſſary for us to offer as the moſt expeditious way for attaining thoſe ends, and that we might clear our ſelves before God and the world, that we have neglected no mean in our power, which may procure a ſpeedy Peace, deſiring much rather to come to a ſpeedy agreement by a friendly conference, then with loſſe of time to reckon up our diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences in writing, although (if the poſture of affairs would have admitted of delay) we ſhould have accounted it our advantage firſt to have preſented to the Houſes in writing the reaſons for the difference of our judgement in the Points controverted.</p>
            <p>Concerning the Propoſition for Religion; When we were ready to have debated with the honourable Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee upon the particulars communicated unto us by dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Houſes upon that Propoſition, their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips did acquaint us that they knew not whether it was the intention of the Houſes to ſend to the King the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances paſt both Houſes, or to ſend any other particulars, and that the Houſes themſelves were to be conſulted here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. And therefore that the Propoſition concerning Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion (the ſetling whereof ſhould be and is the chiefeſt of the deſires of both Kingdoms, and for which principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they entred in ſolemn League and Covenant) may with as diſtinct knowledge and as full aſſurance of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars as is poſſible, be in Name of both Kingdoms deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the King, and with knowledge granted by His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty. And that according to the joynt Declaration of both Kingdoms, Truth and Peace may be eſtabliſhed upon a ſure foundation for the preſent and future Generations; our earneſt deſire is, that a Committee may be appointed with whom we may joyn for conſidering ſuch Articles of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152728:16"/> Reformation, and Uniformity of Church-government, as are already agreed upon by both Houſes, that having joynt conſent, they may be fit matter for the Propoſition of Religion to be ſent to the Kings Majeſty, with ſuch other matters of Church government, as we conceive may be concluded in a day or two, they being long ſince offered to the Houſes, and wherein there can be little difficulty, and the one and the other may be formed up in a Method for a Model of Uniformity in Church-government.</p>
            <p>Without this agreement in particulars of Church-go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, as well as in the Directory of Worſhip and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith, we are not anſwerable to our Covenant; our ingagements and all our labours and ſufferings are in vaine; the very long conſultations of the Divines of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms are fruitleſſe; the great expectation not onely of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but of all the Reformed Churches, is fruſtrated; we ſhall not know what to anſwer to the Church and Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> which will not be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, nor ſecured in their Religion with Generals; nor can we finde any ground to ſatisfie our own reaſon for ſending a general Propoſition of Religion to the King. And therefore we ſtill deſire the honourable Houſes in their wiſdom to expede us of this difficulty, That the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions may be with all ſpeed brought to a comfortable and harmonious concluſion.</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>April</hi> 6. 1646.</date>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:152728:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
